Preliminary Inventory of the Andrew Nagorski interview recordings
Hoover Institution Archives
Andrew Nagorski interview recordings
1976-2008
2017C54
Hoover Institution Archives
4 oversize boxes (130 sound cassettes) (1.7 linear feet)
Interviews of political leaders, dissidents and others, mainly relating to political and social conditions in Poland, other countries of Eastern Europe, and post-Soviet Russia.
Nagorski, Andrew, interviewer.
Access
The collection is open for research.
The Hoover Institution Archives only allows access to copies of audiovisual items, computer media, and digital files. To listen to sound recordings or to view videos, films, or digital files during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all material is immediately accessible.
Acquisition Information
Materials were acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives in 2017.
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog at http://searchworks.stanford.edu/. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in the catalog is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Biographical Note
American journalist; Newsweek foreign correspondent and editor.
Scope and Content of Collection
Interviews of political leaders, dissidents and others, mainly relating to political and social conditions in Poland, other countries of Eastern Europe, and post-Soviet Russia. Many of the interviews from the late 1980s and early 1990s were used not only for Newsweek stories but also for Nagorski's book, The Birth of Freedom (1993).
Name Index
Adamkus, Valdas, 122
Ahtisaari, Martti, 114
Antall, József, 89
Bagsik, Bogusław, 51
Balcerowicz, Leszek, 38
Békesi, László, 91
Biedenkopf, Kurt, 103
Bielecki, Jan Krzysztof, 23
Bielecki, Jerzy, 55
Boguta, Grzegorz, 47
Boross, Péter, 91
Bujak, Zbigniew, 16-21, 44
Burns, Arthur, 107
Busek, Erhard, 123
Bush, George H. W., 119
Čarnogurský, Jan, 84
Celiński, Andrzej, 53
Ciosek, Stanisław, 39
Dienstbier, Jiří, 80, 81, 82
Djilas, Milovan, 108
Dubček, Alexander, 73
Gaidar, Yegor, 58
Gauck, Joachim, 93
Geremek, Bronisław, 44, 45, 46, 81
Göncz, Árpád, 88
Gorbachev, Mikhail, 56, 57
Grigoryants, Sergei, 59
Górnicki, Wiesław, 49
Grynberg, Henryk, 48
Havel, Václav, 69-72
Hegedüs, Ándrás, 87
Hekmatyar, Gulbuddin, 120
Hentosz, Mirosław, 52
Herbst, Lothar, 95
Heym, Stefan, 94
Horn, Gyula, 91
Jeszensky, Gábor, 91
Kaczyński, Jarosław, 23
Kaczyński, Lech, 23
Kapuściński, Ryszard, 24-27
Kaunda, Kenneth, 117
Kavan, Jan, 83
Kelly, Petra, 100
Kertz, Yevgenia, 68
Klaus, Václav, 76
Klein, Klaus and Eva, 102
Knabe, Wilhelm, 101
Kohl, Helmut, 92
Kovács, László, 90
Kozłowski, Krzysztof, 41
Kukliński, Ryszard, 42, 43
Kwaśniewski, Aleksander, 33, 34, 53
Laar, Mart, 110 Lebed, Aleksandr, 60
Lepper, Andrzej, 40 Mály, Václav, 75, 84
Mazowiecki, Tadeusz, 2, 11-15
Mécs, Imre, 85
Medvedev, Roy, 62, 63, 66
Michnik, Adam, 35
Moldan, Bedřich, 79
Nachama, Andreas, 96
Nagorski, Andrew, 124-130
Olechowski, Andrzej, 54
Orbán, Viktor, 86
Özdemir, Cem, 106
Palouš, Martin, 82
Paton, Alan, 118
Prokhanov, Aleksandr, 61
Rácz, Sándor, 85
Rakowski, Mieczysław, 36
Rau, Johannes, 104
Reykowski, Janusz, 37
Saakashvili, Mikheil, 121
Samsonov, Viktor, 68
Sekuła, Ireneusz, 50
Schlögel, Karl, 116
Schröder, Gerhard, 97
Shushkevich, Stanislav, 113
Štěpán, Miroslav, 77, 78
Spielberg, Steven, 31, 32
Stoyanov, Peter, 112
Szymborska, Wisława, 28
Tikhonova, Valentina, 67
Todenhöfer, Jurgen, 105
Uhl, Petr, 74
Voigt, Karsten, 98, 99
Voinovich, Vladimir, 65
Voslensky, Mikhael, 64
Wajda, Andrzej, 29, 30, 44
Wałęsa, Lech, 1-10
Wiesenthal, Simon, 109
Železný, Vladimír, 82
Zhelev, Zhelyu, 111
Zimmermann, Warren, 115
Poland--Politics and government--1989-; Europe, Eastern--Politics and government--1989-; Russia (Federation)--Politics and government--1991-; Audiotapes.
- Poland Interviews
  - Lech Wałęsa
    - Gdańsk, 1985 August 14 (Tape 1)
    - Gdańsk Lenin Shipyard, Wałęsa and Mazowiecki, 1988 May 4 (Tape 2)
    - 1989 November 16 (Tape 3)
    - On campaign trail in Mielec and Rzeszów, 1990 November 2 (Tape 4)
    - 1990 November 8 (Tape 5)
    - 1992 February 6 (Tape 6)
    - 199? August 17 (Tape 7)
    - 1994 June 28 (Tape 8)
    - 1998 November 3 (Tape 9)
    - Visiting U.S., Blair House, 2005? August (Tape 10)
  - Tadeusz Mazowiecki
    - 1990 November 4 (Tape 11)
    - Mazowiecki campaigning in Szczecin, 1990 November 4 (Tape 12)
    - 1992 January 28 (Tape 13)
    - 1992 September 18 (Tape 14)
    - 1990 March 12 (Tape 15)
  - Zbigniew Bujak, 1985 August 19 (Tape 16-21)
    Scope and Contents note
    Extended interview with Bujak while he was still leading the Solidarity underground movement and in hiding. Circumstances of the interview are described in Nagorski's book, The Birth of Freedom.
  - Lech Kaczyński
    - Visit to UN in New York, 2008 September 23 (Tape 22)
    - Jan Krzysztof Bielecki, Jarosław Kaczyński, 1998 January 27 (Tape 23)
  - Ryszard Kapuściński
    - 1990 November 23 (Tape 24)
    - 1991 April 3 (Tape 25)
    - 1994 August 17 (Tape 26)
    - 1999 January 12 (Tape 27)
  - Wisława Szymborska, 1997 January 20 (Tape 28)
    In her apartment in Kraków.
  - Andrzej Wajda (Tape 29)
    - 1996 October 15? (Tape 29)
    - 1999 June 13 (Tape 30)
  - Steven Spielberg
    - 1993 May 4 (Tape 31)
      On set during filming of Schindler’s List in Krakow with Spielberg, Liam Neesen, Ben Kingsley, and Nusia Horowitz (sister of Ryszard Horowitz, both actual members of Schindler’s List, the two children featured in the film and who appear at the end of the film with the other survivors). Nagorski's story about the filming ran in Newsweek.
    - 1994 March 2 (Tape 32)
  - Assorted Polish interviews, batch 1
    - Aleksander Kwaśniewski
      - 1994 May 31 (Tape 33)
      - 1994 January 10 (Tape 34)
    - Adam Michnik, 1991 May 9 (Tape 35)
    - Mieczysław Rakowski, 1988 April 29 (Tape 36)
    - Janusz Reykowski, 1988 April 29 (Tape 37)
    - Leszek Balcerowicz, 1991 October 30 (Tape 38)
    - Stanisław Ciosek, 1991 September 10 (Tape 39)
    - Andrzej Lepper, 1999 November 3 (Tape 40)
    - Krzysztof Kozłowski, 1990 September 6 (Tape 41)
    - Ryszard Kukliński, 1997 October 13 (Tape 42-43)
      Parts 1 and 2 of interview.
  - Assorted Polish interviews, batch 2
    - Andrzej Wajda, Bronisław Geremek, Zbigniew Bujak, 1989 November 3 (Tape 44)
    - Bronisław Geremek
      - 1989 April 26 (Tape 45)
      - 1999 November 5 (Tape 46)
    - Grzegorz Boguta, 1990 November 9 (Tape 47)
      On publishing in the underground.
    - Henryk Grynberg, 1992 February 26 (Tape 48)
    - Wiesław Górnicki, 1990 November 21 (Tape 49)
    - Ireneusz Sekuła, 1990 December 13 (Tape 50)
    - Bogusław Bagsik, 1991 August 7 (Tape 51)
    - Mirosław Hentosz, 1995 October 24 (Tape 52)
    - Andrzej Celiński (side A and part of B) and Aleksander Kwaśniewski (side B), 1991 October 29 (Tape 53)
    - Andrzej Olechowski, 1991 January 21 (Tape 54)
    - Jerzy Bielecki, 1994 October 7 (Tape 55)
- Russia Interviews
  - Mikhail Gorbachev
    - Interview in Novosibirsk, 1995 February 24 (Tape 56)
    - Interview with a few correspondents, 1995 February 24 (Tape 57)
  - Yegor Gaidar, 1994 January 5 (Tape 58)
  - Sergei Grigoryants, 199? July 2 (Tape 59)
  - General Aleksandr Lebed, 199? October 18 (Tape 60)
    Interview conducted in Moldova while he was still in charge of Russian forces there.
  - Aleksandr Prokhanov, 1996 May 15 (Tape 61)
  - Roy Medvedev
    - 1989 February 9 (Tape 62)
    - 1991 April 26 (Tape 63)
  - Michael Voslensky, 1988 January 19 (Tape 64)
  - Vladimir Voinovich, 1995 August 25 (Tape 65)
  - Former Gulag prisoners
    Interview for article that ran in Newsweek International, September 25, 1995.
    - Historian Roy Medvedev (not former prisoner), 1995 September 5 (Tape 66)
    - Valentina Tikhonova, 1995 August 15 (Tape 67)
    - Viktor Samsonov and Yevgenia Kertz, 1995 September 26 (Tape 68)
- Czech and Slovak Interviews
  - Václav Havel
    - 1986 March 28 (Tape 69)
      In his Prague apartment during dissident days.
    - As President, 1991 July 1 (Tape 70)
    - As President, 1993 January 21 (Tape 71)
    - As President, 199 February 10 (Tape 72)
  - Alexander Dubček, 1990 May 14 (Tape 73)
  - Assorted Czech interviews
    - Petr Uhl, 1987 October 27 (Tape 74)
    - Václav Mály, 1991 January 9 (Tape 75)
    - Václav Klaus, 1990 October 16 (Tape 76)
    - Miroslav Štěpán, 1991 October 7 (Tape 77-78)
    - Bedřich Moldan, 1991 September 23 (Tape 79)
    - Jiří Dienstbier, 1992 June 10 (Tape 80)
    - Dienstbier and Geremek, 1994 November 11 and 15 (Tape 81)
    - Dienstbier, Martin Palouš, Vladimir Železný, 1990 October 15 (Tape 82)
    - Jan Kavan, 1991 September 24 (Tape 83)
    - Jan Čarnogurský (Slovakia, side A) and Václav Mály (side B), 1991 January 7 and 9 (Tape 84)
- Hungary Interviews
  - Imre Mécs and Sándor Rácz, 1986 October 7 (Tape 85)
    Veterans of 1956 revolution on 30th anniversary.
  - Prime Minister Viktor Orbán, 1998 September 10 (Tape 86)
  - András Hegedüs, undated (Tape 87)
  - President Árpád Göncz, 1990 May 18 (Tape 88)
  - Prime Minister József Antall, 1991 October 21 (Tape 89)
  - Foreign Minister László Kovács, 1997 July 8 (Tape 90)
    Interview in Madrid.
  - Gyula Horn, László Békesi, Gábor Jeszensky, Péter Boross, 1994 April 21 (Tape 91)
- Germany Interviews
  - Helmut Kohl, 1986 October 16 (Tape 92)
    Joint interview with Newsweek editor Maynard Parker. Interview caused an uproar because of Kohl’s comparison of Gorbachev’s PR technique to Joseph Goebbels.
  - Joachim Gauck, 1999 October 12 (Tape 93)
  - Stefan Heym (East German writer), 1987 September 11 (Tape 94)
  - Lothar Herbst, 1987 October 19 (Tape 95)
    During his stay in Germany.
  - Andreas Nachama, 1998 May 11 (Tape 96)
  - Gerhard Schröder, 1999 April 13 (Tape 97)
  - Karsten Voigt
    - Social Democrats, 1997 May 7 (Tape 98)
      Should include the story of his wife who had informed on him for the Stasi. Nagorski wrote an article about this that appeared in the June 23, 1997 issue of Newsweek.
    - 1987 January 9 (Tape 99)
  - Petra Kelly, Greens, 1985 April 26 (Tape 100)
  - Wilhelm Knabe, Greens, 1987 August 28 (Tape 101)
  - Klaus and Eva Klein (Berlin Wall escapees), 1999 January 26 (Tape 102)
  - Kurt Biedenkopf, 1996 October 21 (Tape 103)
  - Johannes Rau, 1986 November 13 (Tape 104)
  - Jurgen Todenhöfer, 1984 April 23 (Tape 105)
  - Cem Özdemir, 1999 August 19 (Tape 106)
  - Arthur Burns (U.S. ambassador), 1985 March 13 (Tape 107)
- Miscellaneous Interviews
  - Milovan Djilas, 1987 October 6 (Tape 108)
  - Simon Wiesenthal, 1994 February (Tape 109)
  - Estonian Prime Minister Mart Laar, 1994 March 17 (Tape 110)
  - Bulgarian President Zhelyu Zhelev, early 1990s? (Tape 111)
  - Bulgarian President Peter Stoyanov, 1996 November 23 (Tape 112)
  - Stanislav Shushkevich (Minsk), 1994 February 1 (Tape 113)
  - Martti Ahtisaari, 1999 June 11 (Tape 114)
  - Warren Zimmermann (head of US delegation to OSCE), 1986 October 28 (Tape 115)
  - Karl Schlögel (German writer on concept of Mitteleuropa), 1987 March 9 (Tape 116)
  - Kenneth Kaunda (President of Zambia, Lusaka), 1976 October 13 (Tape 117)
  - Alan Paton (anti-apartheid activist, Durban, South Africa), 1976 October 16 (Tape 118)
  - Ex-President George H.W. Bush, undated (Tape 119)
    Brief testimonial for Polish edition of Newsweek.
  - Gulbuddin Hekmatyar (Afghan rebel leader), 1985 November 13 (Tape 120)
  - Mikheil Saakashvili, 2004 September 23 (Tape 121)
  - Lithuanian President Valdas Adamkus, 1999 March 8 (Tape 122)
  - Erhard Busek (Austrian politician, on Mittleeuropa), 1987 February 10 (Tape 123)
- Radio Interviews about Soviet Union and Eastern Europe
  - Pat McCann Show, WOR NY, 1982 August 27 (Tape 124)
  - Diane Rehm Show, WAMU
    - 1988 August 24 (Tape 125)
      Labor unrest in Poland.
    - 1989 June 6 (Tape 126)
      Poland elections.
  - Fiske Show, WAMU, 1985 October 30 (Tape 127)
    Soviet Union. Two parts.
  - Cuthbert Show, WAMU, 1989 August 25 (Tape 128)
    Eastern Europe.
  - "Newsweek" on Air, 1985 March 31 (Tape 129)
  - Radio show, Nagorski’s expulsion from Soviet Union, circa 1980s (Tape 130)